懒人
游戏
评测
本期任务是：
搭建台 486 DOS 电脑！
大家好啊，欢迎大家来看LGR七周年纪念！这可太疯狂了！
Greetings, and welcome to LGR for 7 years now! What a crazy thing!
说到疯狂，你们看见开头的群魔乱舞了吗?那才是最好玩的！
Speaking of crazy things, did you hear that intro? That is just the coolest!
感谢Andrew Hulshult帮忙制作开头的BGM！
Huge shoutout to Andrew Hulshult for putting that together for me.
我委托他将我的老主题曲Vaxeen 4U按照我的意见重新混音，你们刚才也听见了。这可确实不错！
I commissioned him to remix my old theme song Vaxeen 4U in this mental rendition, as you just heard and it is awesome!
你如果乐意的话，你可以在下面说明中下载整曲，并且欣赏他的其他大作。他的作品确实不错。但是呢
You can download the whole thing in the description below if you like and check out his other music too, he does a lot of really good stuff, but...
更加感谢你们多年的支持！
Big shoutout to all of you as well.
你们多年的支持，让我度过了人生中最好的时光！我十分温暖。
Supporting the show over the years, this has just been the best time of my life. I love doing this.
我将尽我所能继续做下去，现在我要通过一些微小的
I'm going to keep doing this as long as I can and I just wanna repay you a little bit by
你们长期想让我的视频来回报你们。
doing a video that you've requested for a long time
这件事我也想了很多年了，它就是......
and something that I've wanted to do for ages myself, and that is...
装个 486 DOS 游戏电脑。而且我想干的原因是
Build a 486 computer for MS-DOS gaming and I am to do this because...
你懂得，我小时侯用的就是这种电脑而且
You know, this is the kind of era of computers that I was just like in awe of as a kid and
你可以用它来干很多很酷的事情除了学习 :-） ！所以呢现在我们将要
there's so many cool things you can do with them! So we're just going to...
开始将装机过程中遇到的麻烦一一解决
Go all out and really explain the pros and cons and the hassles that you're going to have to deal with,
并且看看我们能用这台电脑干什么。
but also the excitement and the cool stuff that you can do with a 486 computer.
再感受自己装机的乐趣:-)
And the pleasures of building one yourself.
不仅如此，我还得装出LGR的范儿。
And not only that, I'm gonna deck it out in the only way I know how to on LGR.
现在有请木纹贴纸！
And that is with woodgrain.
没错！就是木纹贴纸！
That's right! Woodgrain!
在我的节目中，它不俗气，他很优雅！
On this show, it's not tacky, it's *classy*!
我搞到这些Contact牌纸啊，木纹啊，乙烯胶啊
And I'm just got this contact paper...  woodgrain... vinyl adhesive,
然后用它贴出90年代米色风格，让他看起来十分顺眼！
and we're just gonna wrap a 90's kind of beige-style case in this, and make it look awesome!
像这个我装饰的外置三吋半软驱！
Kind of like what I did to this  3½ inch external floppy drive here!
就像这样！
Just look at that.
这个感官提升十分明显。不得不说，我喜欢木纹。
That is just a marked improvement, I have got to say. I like woodgrain.
现在我来快速谈谈我为何要攒这台486。我的目的是啥？
And allow me to explain really quick what I want to do with this 486. What are my goals here?
译者注：加速键介绍视频：av17110874
一方面，老机器有加速键。我觉得很酷。
Well, for one thing, it's gotta have a turbo button. I think that's just cool.
第二个方面，我希望电脑上有VESA总线（现今PCI-E显卡接口发明前的显卡接口），诸如VESA兼容主板和有
And two, I want it to be a VESA local bus, like VESA-compatible motherboard and computer with
一个有VLB（VESA Local Bus）连接支持的显卡，因为我小时候特别渴求。
a video card that uses a VLB connector because it was something I always just sort of lusted after as a kid,
在SimCity 2000发行后我还没有一个能输出SVGA的VESA兼容电脑。
after SimCity 2000 came out and I didn't have a VESA-compatible computer that did SVGA.
然后我想着这件事直到我知道它们只是普通的16位ISA卡，但是呢
And so, that just stuck in my mind for years and I know there were just regular 16-bit ISA cards, and...
它们依然很酷，但是我仍然想要。因为我从未有过，而且这个将会十分有趣。
Those are cool too, but I wanna mess with VLB because I never have and it seems like it could be interesting.
还有，我只是想让它与93-94年的大众机相适应
The other goal really is just to keep it kinda period accurate to around 1993-1994.
这也是我想与那时相适应，反正......你明白，这也许不是我攒过的最强劲的486 DOS电脑
Something that I would have respected back then, but... you know,  maybe it's not the most powerhouse DOS 486 I could build;
实际上，它确实不是。
In fact, I know it's not.
所以你也许会失望，但是呢，在装配DOS电脑时你可以随意搭配，
So you may be disappointed in that, but you know, there are just infinite variations on DOS computer builds that you can do.
并且这也将会将很多基本操作都涉及到，你也可以在攒更强劲的机器时使用这些方法。
This will just kinda cover a whole lot of the basics, though. And you can apply this to the more powerful builds.
也许将来我也会那么做。
And uh, maybe I'll do that sometime in the future too.
现在，让我们走入正文！
But yeah, let's just hop into some part selection!
我相信肯定有人要问我哪里能搞到这些配件，
I'm sure someone's gonna ask where am I gonna get the parts for this computer, and...
额，这是个好问题。可以上ebay，也可以泡论坛，或者呢......去淘二手（例如GoodWill）。
Uh, that's a good question. I could go to eBay, I could go to forums, or... try to look for them in thrift stores.
但是我有个好地方。
But I have a better option.
为何不去仓库找找呢？因为，额，我不常展示这个。
Why not just look in my own storage? Because um, well, you know, I don't show people this very often,
但是这里有许多东西躺在地上。盒子里呢倒是有些
but I've got a few spares of things lying around. These boxes are just full of parts,
软件啊，正在进行的项目啊，好多以前完成的LGR视频素材啊，还有未来将要完成的计划呢。
software, ongoing projects, a lot of LGR things I've done in the past and many things I hope to cover in the future.
或者只是乱七八糟的东西，诸如这里一堆ISA什么的卡。
Or even just a box of stuff like this here, just random ISA and other cards.
里面啥都有。声卡啊，显卡啊。
All sorts of things in here: Sound cards, video cards...
这是个Voodoo牌显卡。
This is a Voodoo card...
咱来看看这是个啥？
Let's see, which one is this?
额，比我要找东西的年代要新，但里面还是干货满满的。
Yeah, a lot of these are maybe a little later than what I'm looking for, but there's also some good stuff in here.
我将一定会用......
I'm for sure gonna use...
啊，这里有个......原版的声霸卡（现在十分稀有），这很好。
Oh, here's a... it's an original SoundBlaster. That'd be nice.
啊，这些装备难道不耐人吗？
Well, isn't this a lovely assortment of parts?
来，咱们来一个个欣赏，它们都是很耐人欣赏的。
Let's just go ahead and take a look at everything, piece by piece, because I think it's awesome.
这是一块我们将用的主板，显然，这是我们电脑的基本框架。
And here is the motherboard itself that we will be using, which is quite an important piece, obviously.
这里呢，如果你对型号好奇的话，这里写的应该是VI15G。
This right here, if you're curious about the model, is the something known as the VI15G.
记得好像是啥时由宏碁生产的，但是呢......我忘了:-(
I believe it was manufactured by Acer at some point or another, but... yeah, I don't know,
宏碁制造
建碁贴牌
就是那种那时常见的通用 Socket 3 486 主板
it's just your kind of generic jack-of-all-trades Socket 3 486 motherboard that's very common at the time.
当然，我用这个主板是有原因的。首先是其是VLB兼容的，
There's a few reasons that I went with it, of course, first being that it has VLB capability, which is just something
我从没搞过这个，所以我对这个很好奇。
that I haven't messed with very much, so I'm curious to do that.
这里基本是16位ISA插槽的扩展，也就是这些插槽了。
It's basically an extension of 16-bit ISA, which is what all these slots are here.
这些是扩展插槽，并且呢
These are your expansion slots and um... well...
这还要一些附加插槽，所以这个不是PCI之类的东西。
You have this in addition to that, so it's not PCI or anything like that.
这只是兼容VLB的16位ISA插槽，所以你可以在此插入诸如显卡之类的，当然，这也是我将要做的。
It's just 16-bit ISA with VLB capability, so you can plug in things like, well, video cards, of course, which is what I'm gonna be using,
当然这也有硬盘控制器和
but also hard disk controllers and uh...
像串口，并口，诸如此类的东西。当然，我更加关注的是视频输出。
like COM, serial connections and all sorts of things, but...  pretty much just want it for the video capability right now.
这里还有零插入力插座Socket 3。
It also has this nice zero-insertion force socket 3.
这里呢，是插CPU用的。
Right here, for the CPU.
而且它可以让你将CPU安装到位，跟现在攒机一样，也没啥奇怪的，
And that just allows you to drop it in place, which is pretty much what you see still nowadays and that might not seem so weird,
但实际上，当年很多板子上没有这个，你得自己把它装到位，这个的确烦人:-(
but actually, there's a lot of boards at the time that don't have this, and you kinda have to jam it in place. It's really annoying.
然后呢，如果你要装风扇的话，这里有个辅助接口。
Uh, it's got a nice little auxiliary thing here,  if you wanna plug in like a fan or something.
不过当时谁会用呢？
Uh... Who cares?
这里也有AMI的BIOS，这个呢...:-D我只是喜欢这个简洁的版本:-)
And there's also this American Megatrends BIOS, which they :-D I just like this particular version of it because it looks neat.
这玩意有图形界面，挺让我高兴。（译者注：同是AMI，为何我这11年的倒没有！）当我们设定程序时用处很大。
It's got a UI that just pleases me. And we'll get to that when we get to the setup program.
这里呢，好像是缓存芯片啥的吧......
Uh, it's got a spot here for like cache memory chips...
我不知道现在我手里有没有，但我稍后去库里看看。
I don't know if I have any of those on hand at the moment, but I will check to see if I do later.
再来看看这些针脚，这些跳线之类的。
Um... and check out all these little pins, right, all these jumpers.
这一大堆针脚和跳线不是被断开就是被短路。
There are *sooo* many pins and jumpers and things that either have to be opened or shorted or whatever.
那些东西呢实际上是配置......诸如CPU类型，速度，
And that actually configures... like what your CPU type is, the speed,
其他你安装的东西，或是你想激活与否的之类的。
other things you may have installed or features you want to enable or disable.
刚才说到的都由跳线控制，其余的就是BIOS的事了。
It's all through pins, and the rest of it's through the BIOS.
这里还有很多诸如设置程序之类的在里面，但是呢
There's a lot more going on in like the setup program in this one, but...
好多东西还得折腾这些跳线:-(
Yeah, there's still a lot of stuff to determine through pins.
然后这是72针SIMM内存槽。
Uh, it's got four 72-pin SIMM RAM slots here.
这个板子适配16位内存。在当时还有好些板子用的是30针SIMM内存槽，
And this is 16-bit RAM. There's a lot of the boards at the time that are still gonna have 30-pin SIMM slots,
但这个是有72针的插座，我十分喜欢。
but this one has the 16, like the 72-pin ones. I like that.
我记得好像它最高支持96MB内存，在当年算是海量了。
I think this'll actually take up to like 96 megs of RAM, which is *insane.*
现在我不装满它，但是想想还是很酷的，不是吗？
I'm not gonna put that much, although it would be kinda cool, wouldn't it?
这个呢，如果你对现在电脑硬件熟悉的话，你或许对这个没那么熟悉。
This right here might not look familiar if you're just more familiar with more modern PCs.
这个不是现在用的ATX电源插座，这个只是传统的PC电源插座，所以说呢......
This is not ATX or anything. That is your traditional  PC power supply connector right there, so...
好吧。
Yeah.
有点意思。
That's fun.
有点...怎么说呢...很难对付的吧。
A little uh, little aggravating to deal with.
实际上，你会注意到这个板子上缺少许多接口。
You'll notice there's a severe lack of ports built into this thing, in fact,
尤其是这里仅有的一个输入输出接口......一个5针键盘接口，然后就没啦！
really, the only I/O kind of thing you have right here is...  a keyboard, for 5-pin AT keyboard stuff, and that's it!
所以呢，像诸如鼠标啊，显示屏啊，喇叭啊，基本上所有的东西，硬盘啊，你都要插卡来支持:-(
So, for things like, you know, a mouse or graphics card , sound, or literally anything, hard disk support, you're gonna need cards.
到处都要控制卡，所以这也是为嘛这里有如此多的插槽，因为好多基本功能板上没有。
Cards everywhere, so that's why there's so many friggin' slots because pretty much every basic function is just not built in
而且在那时这可是常见现象！
and that's very common for these boards at the time!
在那时板子也不算常见的是这个CR2032纽扣电池。
And something else that isn't common for boards of this era necessarily is the CR2032.
用来给CMOS和
Just your basic kind of battery for the CMOS...
板上实时时间供电用的。现在很常见，但是，你知道吗？
and real time clock and that's...  common now, but uh, you know what?
这是我拥有的那时唯一有这个功能的主板。
This is the only board like this from this time period that I actually own.
实际上，现在我展示的是我考虑过的其他主板。
In fact, let me show you some of the others that I was considering.
这是考虑之一。你看，这俩在很多方面十分相似，但看看这个。
So this board right here. It's very similar in a lot of ways, but look at that.
这上面有这个超级恐怖的柱状电池，还被焊在板上:-(
It's got that *horrible* like barrel battery and its soldered into the board and...
搞下来倒不是啥大问题。实际上，我想直接把它剪下来，因为
It's not a huge pain to take off of there. In fact, I've just been meaning to clip it off, because...
这玩意它漏液！而且会进而毁掉这个板子，还会腐蚀掉电路......反正后果严重。
They leak. And they will *ruin* the motherboard and eat into the traces, it's just... a bad time all around.
译者注：此有极佳例子：av11192843
所以呢，离这些玩意越远越好！
So uh... yeah.... Just get rid of  those things whenever you can.
或者用......诸如CR2032纽扣电池替换。你可以把它们焊在对应位置，这也不难。
Or replace them with... like the CR2032, you can solder in a holder, it's no big deal.
这个需要一个特别的PCB塑料板
来防止放电短路！
这里还有一些缓存芯片。也许我可以尝试将这些芯片用在其他主板上。
There's some of those cache chips. I might actually try to use those in the other board, hm.
现在我来展示另一个我考虑过的主板。
And let me show you one other motherboard I was considering here...
但我决定不用，因为这个电池......还是电池问题。
But decided against, because of the battery... mainly.
嗯，实际上呢，板子是不错，但它上面的
Um, this is a really nice little board, actually, but it has that...
这个CPU插座就有点......
CPU insertion right there that is just...
我是说，这就是那种教你使劲装到位，而且也没有手把儿。这让装CPU变得十分痛苦。而且呢......
I mean, you just kinda have to slam it in place and there's no lever, it makes it really annoying to deal with and whatever...
我懒我任性:-)
just being lazy.
而且这上面还有这种电池。
And then its got this, which is the battery.
这是众多实时时钟之一。许多由Dallas工厂制造（@David Murray）。
It's one of these real-time clocks.  Lot of them were made by Dallas.
而且电池就放在这个小玩意里......
And it's just all inside this... little thing here, and...
最恼人的是尽管它能在内力耗尽前坚挺很长时间，但收尸时呢......
The annoying thing is even though they last a really long time, when they do die... look at that!
这玩意底下针脚真多，而且是直接焊在板上的！
There's a billion little pins underneath and it's soldered directly under the board.
幸亏现在的都给焊上了插座，处理起来轻松了很多。
Now, some of them are socketed. Those aren't a huge pain to deal with, of course,
直接拔出然后插个新的，然后万事大吉。
you can just pull 'em out, put in a new one. Everything's fine.
但这个呢，你得有个趁手的玩意，诸如真空去焊机之类的东西才能处理。
But with this one, you need like, proper...  like a vacuum pump desoldering tool.
我手上嘛......反正没有，我也不想处理，所以嘛
I just- I don't have that, I don't wanna deal with it, so...
就用这个了。换个纽扣电池还是很方便的。
Went with this one... with the nice little easily replaceable CR2032.
反正现在到处都能搞到:-)
So... you can get those batteries frickin' anywhere nowadays.
（此处应该是LGR在说胡话，我没太看懂，有更好的翻译请弹幕覆盖）
And, since ever the dawn of time, in fact, I think those 2032s predate humanity.
来，看看下一个大件是啥?
So uh, let's see, what's up next here?
我想我可以介绍CPU了。
I guess we can just go onto the CPU itself.
然后，我将用这个AMD YES！
And, I'm going with an AMD,
在那时，它们经常比Intel的快那么一丢丢。所以这相关的香啊！
which at the time, these were actually... a little bit faster than a lot of Intel's offerings. So these things are really neat!
这个型号DX2-66，AM486插槽版本。
This is the DX2-66, the AM486 version of it.
而且呢......这个就是好，就是YES！
And um... well, it's- it's pretty awesome.
一款十分经典的芯片。
Really classic chip.
经典速度，更重要的是，
Classic speed, and most importantly,
我的主板能直接支持，十分自然。
my motherboard supports it right...  er, out of the box, like just as it is.
所以，这使装机变得很优雅:-)
So... that makes it really easy.
而明显的是，如果你想升级的话（你肯定会的）。实际上，我也考虑到这个性能怪兽，大家看看。
Um, obviously, if you can get something better, you probably want to. In fact, I was also considering this monster, look at this.
这是AMD的，型号Am486 DX4-100。
This is Am486 DX4-100.
可笑的是，这玩意性能很强，可以甩Intel早期奔腾九万八千里，
Ridiculously， powerful for the time, in fact, this thing can give early Pentiums a run for their money...
而且吊杀Intel的DX4-100s处理器:-)(译者注：本应如此)
and outperform the DX4-100s from Intel.
再看这，这玩意要散热器！
Check that! Heatsink was actually required for this one, whereas...
再看看这DX2就不需要，
Just like the uh, DX2, is not,
所以你不必再装散热装置，但这个嘛，就得装了。
so you don't need any heatsinks or fans or anything, but this one, heatsink and fan would be nice.
当然，我也可以给DX2装散热器。
Uh, I could add a heatsink and fan to the DX2 if I wanted...
实际上，我手里就有一个。就这小玩意。
Um, in fact, I've got one right here.  Look at this little thing.
“多么耐人啊:-)”它能用。我只能讲到这了。
"Oh, how cute." It works. That's about as much as I can say for it.
好的，为了让我们需要装的东西能用，我拿出来了这个标准的控制卡。
Alright, so in order to get capability of pretty much everything we need, I've got this standard kind of controller card.
这张16位ISA控制卡能让电脑用硬盘、软盘和串并口。
16-bit ISA and it gives us hard disk and floppy disk capability as well, as parallel and serial port.
还有另一个串口，和一个大概是16针游戏手柄口。
Another serial port, and then like a 16-pin game port here, looks like, which...
这大概对装声卡来说有点多余，但是呢，
will be kind of redundant once I install a sound card, but hey!
这样很好！这样我的接口就很多了:-)说真的。
That's nice! That adds a bunch of I/O that we really need. Seriously.
来，咱看看这个。嗯，这是个硬盘，十分不错。
And... let's see here. Ah well, we got the hard disk, which is *awesome*.
这是个经典的西部数据 Caviar 2420，一个有着超大425.3MB存储的硬盘。我的天啊！
This is a classic Western Digital Caviar 2420...  a massive 425.3 megabytes. Oh man!
94年4月生产，所以，应该很合适。
April 1994 was when this was made, so, seemed appropriate.
我也想过搞个CF卡当存储。我也关注过，但是呢,
I could have gone with a CompactFlash solution. I'm very well aware of that, but...
总觉得不合适。
uh, just didn't want to.
我想搞点更多的原始件来攒，而且呢，
I wanted to go with more original kind of stuff here and also...
我在处理CF卡与DOS适配方面出过许多奇奇怪怪的问题。
I've had some weird issues with CompactFlash and DOS and things actually...
有时跑得慢，有时不稳定。
sometimes running a little slower or just being iffy.
Errr，反正我没法让DOS在CF卡上工作。
I don't know. I just didn't wanna mess with it for a DOS machine.
我也不太想用，因为它们不太快。
And I don't really need it either because... honestly, that thing's fast enough.
我也喜欢老硬盘工作时的噪音。
I like the sound of old hard disks too.
这是我们将会用的内存，72针的。
Here's the RAM we'll be going with, a 72-pin here.
这一条8M，所以搭配DX2处理器的呢是16M的内存。
This one is 8 megs and uh... so is this one, so we're  going to have 16 megabytes of RAM with a 486 DX2.
这配置过于经典，以至于我高兴得都要跳起来了。
That is just such a classic configuration that it makes me wanna dance around.
现在为你带来的是我们将要用的显卡。
Uh, let's see here. We've got...  the video card that we're going to be using
而且呢，我这有很多VLB显卡，但这个呢是我有的
and, wow, there are a lot of choices for VLB video cards, but this is one of 'em that I had...
适合攒机的中品相比较好的。
on hand that is uh, quite nice, I think, for what I'm wanting to do.
这个是Diamond SpeedStar Pro VLB，有1M显存。
This is the Diamond SpeedStar Pro VLB. This is a 1 megabyte video card.
这张卡完美无瑕啊！它能输出SVGA和VGA信号，应该能适配EGA和CGA信号，确实不错。
It's pretty sweet. And it supplies uh, the SVGA and VGA and I think pretty good compatibility with like EGA and CGA, which is... nice.
当然，我也有其他的显卡，有的有2M显存。
But yeah, there's a whole bunch of other cards, some of them are 2 megs,
有几个还有4M显存，这都可以扮猪吃老虎了。但是呢......
couple are even... seeing like 4 meg,  I mean, that's ridiculous, but...
再来看看这里的VLB连接口，就在这个经典的8位ISA连接口后面。
Yeah, so it's got the VLB connector right here, in addition to your classic sort of 8-bit style ISA connector.
我也把这个拿了出来因为我将来也许会搞些网络之类的事情，
I'm also gonna slap this in here because I might play around with some networking at some point, so...
所以我追加了这个：10/100网卡，这可是个好玩意。
we've got this to add here: 10/100 Ethernet and all that good stuff, so that's cool.
但是你懂得，这就是张卡，也没啥的。
But it's just, you know, it's just a card. Kind of boring.
这张卡就有趣多了。
This is not boring though.
当说到声卡的时候，显然我有说不尽的话头，
When it comes to sound cards, there are obviously a *ton* of things I thought about,
你懂得，原版声霸卡啊，Sound Blaster 16啊，实际上，
you know, the original Sound Blaster, Sound Blaster 16, in fact...
我也还在想插个Sound Blaster 16在这呢，
I'm still considering slapping like a Sound Blaster 16 in here,
但是呢。我更想搞个这个：AWE32声卡，这个AWE32 CT3900声卡。
but you know what? I may as well just go with this: the AWE 32, the AWE32 CT3900.
能输出老式波表合成音乐和其他的好东西。
Good old wavetable sound and all sorts of just cool stuff.
这张卡十分有名，那时我十分想要一张。现在我终于可以装一个了，因为现在我有了<(￣︶￣)>
These cards were legendary, always wanted one back in the day, and I've got one I'm gonna stick it in there because I *caaan*.
当然，这个也需要插内存，大概30针。如果我心情好的话，兴许我会插几根的。
And yes, this does actually take some RAM in here, like 30-pin. I might stick some in there if I feel like it.
我也想装个Gravis Ultrasound之类的声卡，可惜我没有。
I would've loved to put like a Gravis Ultrasound, but I don't own one.
要有张多好啊......可惜了，
I would *love* to have it- one, but...
它们很贵而且很难找，所以说，改天再说吧。但这个能工作。
Uh... they're expensive and hard to track down, so. Maybe someday. But this'll work.
最后呢，这里有些驱动器。
And then, lastly, we've got some drives here.
这里有个三吋半的，1.44M的软盘驱动器，十分普通.
Uh, so, we've got 3½ inch, just your 1.44 meg. Very standard.
还有这个，一个标准的大软驱。这个应该是可以用1.2M的。
And... also very standard 5¼ inch. And this one is... 1.2 megabyte capable.
而且我太喜欢了！看看这里！
And I like that. Hey, look at that.
"本驱动器无需保护纸保护，强行插入会损坏机械结构！"
"This drive is designed *not* to require a protect sheet. Inserting one may damage the mechanism."
我不想把这个撕下来，因为这个增添了某种魅力。
I don't want to take that off of there, because it adds some... charm.
某种过时的魅力。
Like very outdated charm.
那时在你移动这个驱动器时，你通常会插一张软盘形状的硬卡纸
At one point, when you were moving these things around, you would actually stick like a piece of floppy disk-shaped cardboard
来保证里面的部件不会咯咯作响。
in there to keep the internals from rattling when you're moving the computer.
但是，这个就不需要了。
But uh, they don't need it anymore with this one.
如果你关心这个是那生产之类的，这个是“CHINON”......不太会念。型号FR506。
And in case you're wondering about like the manufacturing and stuff, this is a Chinon... I don't know how. FR506.
十分普通的软驱，我这有好几个。
Very common floppy drive. I've seen quite a few of these around.
然后这个也是一个十分基本的CD光驱。
And this is pretty much just the most basic CD-ROM drive.
Errr，我对这个不怎么满意，但是，这是我拥有的最接近这个时代的了。
Um, I'm not the happiest with this, but, it's what I had lying around closest by.
所以......你懂得。
So... you know.
这是个94年生产的索尼大法CDU331-01双倍速光驱，所以这应该很合适。
This is just a Sony CDU331-01 double speed CD-ROM drive made in 1994, so it seemed appropriate.
然后是这个，即将呈现的是————这个机箱！
And then, last but not least... is the case!
这个不过是个机箱。
It's pretty much just a case.
拆掉外壳，你就看见了里面是这样。
Taken off the outside here so you can see the inside.
并且呢，这就是那时的普遍设计，装这玩意也有一些烦人之处。
and... uh, it's just your kind of typical design of the time and its got some annoying stuff too,
比如这个用来固定硬盘啥的小盒子，想想装它就很烦人。
like a big caddy here for holding the hard disks and whatnot. Ah, just... ergh.
但是呢，其他部分还是很喜人的，比如这里小巧玲珑的蜂鸣器。
But, hey. I like the other parts of it. I like the fact that it has a nice, proper PC speaker in there.
一个完美的锥形蜂鸣器，不是现在许多现在机器有的垃圾压力蜂鸣器。
Um, a nice... cone. None of that Piezo beeper crap that you see on a lot of modern machines.
这个机箱呢，也附带一个电源，
And then, of course, we have the power supply...
200瓦的，由Bestec生产？
which is just a 200 watt power supply by Bestec?
也不知是否品质优良（Best），但很明显很有科技范（Tech）。
I don't know if it is the "best," but it's definitely "tech."
还有这前面板，我十分喜欢这个设计。
And then around front here, I really like the front design of this.
这一排凸起，吸引人的......不管了，辞藻缺乏了。
That whole sort of ridge- riveting, whatever, I don't know.
确实不错！
It's neat!
我喜欢这个显示屏，这个对我很有必要因为
I like the display, the display was a necessary thing for me because...
我从小就认为这个很酷。
I just thought it was the coolest thing ever as a kid.
哦，这已经有个软驱了:-|
Uh, it's got a floppy drive already in here.
你懂的，我就把它放着吧因为把它弄出来很费劲。
You know, I might just leave it in there because it's really annoying to get out of here.
我看看这能不能用，如果行的话，我就将其放这了。
I'll see if it works, and if it does, I'll probably just leave it.
接下来的呢，是这个“加速”键。这个也很重要。
But, uh, check it out. Turbo button, cause that's awesomely necessary.
然后呢，这里还有个锁来锁上键盘，防止那些搞乱的小孩之类的吧。
And uh, it does have the key right here for locking the keyboard and people from messing with it and whatnot.
实际上，看看这里。
In fact, check this out.
我配到了这个锁的钥匙。
I've actually got the keys to go with it.
所以呢，你就将其插入这里，
So uh... you just stick that in the front there...
将其锁上然后没人能动你的电脑了。
turn the key and then nobody's gonna be using your computer.
如果你忘了开锁的话，电脑会拒绝开机。你就回想：“嘛玩意？”
Or if you forget and leave it in the wrong position, then your computer's just not turning on. You're like, "What the heck!?"
或者键盘用不了，就很不好。
Or the keyboard doesn't work. It sucks.
我也很喜欢这个标志，“486DX2 66 megahertz”。
I like that little badge too, 486DX2 66 megahertz.
现在该开始装这个CPU了！（译者注：终于开始装机了 8-| ）
Now it is time to insert this CPU.
然后呢，在装机之前，请让我强调一下静电放电的事情
And uh, before I go any further though, let me just address the whole electrostatic discharge thing because
因为你们会注意到我没戴腕带，我向来认为我不需要这个。
you may have noticed I'm not wearing a wriststrap or anything, I've never felt the need to.
我这么做好几年了，也没出问题。我只是摸一下接地的电脑机箱底盘。
I've been doing this for decades, no problem at all, just touching a computer chassis that's grounded-
来放走静电并且不要在不绝缘的面上工作。
making sure you discharge your static and not doing anything on like a static...
这个木质桌子就很合适。
surface or anything and this wood table is fine.
反正你们得在意这个，保证你们不会触电啥的。
Uh, you just gotta be mindful of it though, of course, and make sure that you are discharging and uh...
你懂的，你要做好......话头不对劲，赶紧刹车。
You know, make sure that- *Laughter* That sounds really dirty, let's just stop it right there.
所以无论如何，这是CPU然后我们如何放在槽中呢？好吧，这没那么复杂。
So anyway, uh, here is the CPU itself and how do we do this? Well, it's pretty simple.
你要注意一下这个缺角，这将是你安装的方向。
If you see that little notch cutout right there, that's letting you know which way to put this thing in.
然后这将会那个小针槽对齐，那个确实有点孤独伤感:-(
And that's supposed to line up with that little extra pin that's off to the side there, being alone and sad,
然后呢我们将CPU放入，然后你们会发现插槽中有更多比CPU上的针脚的更多的槽。
so we just sort of drop it here and you'll notice that there are actually more holes in this socket than there are pins on the CPU.
你就把它放在这正中间就好了嘛。
You just sort of stick it very much in the middle right there...
然后放好就万事大吉了。
and then uh, we'll just drop this in place and that's it.
CPU就装好了！
We've installed the CPU!
好的，该装内存了。
Alright, time to address the RAM.
装这个玩意呢......也很有趣，主要是这些小凹槽。
And these are er, kind of fun too, as far as little notches go.
这也就意味着只能照着一定方向插入主板。
So that means it can only go in one way here and in this particular board,
而这里有较那里更多的针脚（译者注：是不是指反了？），这也意味着要如此方式对应。
there's like a little extra bit on this side and not on this side, so that means the slot's gonna go over there.
好的，对于这个呢，我要将其插入插槽1，
And uh... so with this one, I'm going to put this one in slot 1,
按主板上的标识，应该是最下面的那个。
which is this first one down here, which is labeled on the motherboard.
然后应该如此滑入。
And uh, it should just go in like so.
然后嘿喂狗，这就就是这样就位的。
There you go. It just sort of snaps in place there and gets in like that
然后你会想让他们完美紧密地，因为它们
and you do want to make sure that it's nice and tight, because these are...
需要细细注意。有时它们看似插好，实际未必。
Uh... a little finicky. Sometimes they're- it look like it's in, but it's not.
就像这样。
There we go.
感觉它们装到位了吧......好了，下一步。
Felt everything snap in place, I think, so... alright.
内存已装好，所以下一站是机箱，我们开始装控制卡！
Got the RAM installed, so let's get this thing inside the case, then we can start installing some cards!
那么这里也有一个现在不常见的设计。
So here's another thing that you don't see a whole lot of anymore
这里只有两个螺母固定主板。
and that is the fact that there's only two offsets for the motherboard in this case.
而剩下的是这种小插槽，是用来固定这种塑料卡扣的。
Otherwise, you'd just have these little grooves here and that's for these kind of plastic offsets and uh,
你瞧，这还挺有意思的。因为呢
you know, it's kind of interesting... because...
就这种清脆的声音。
They just sort of... pop in here...
像这样。
Like that.
然后呢，它们将要......
And then, they're going to uh....
这个部分将要滑入插槽的后面。那么这里有四个。
that part is going to slide into... these little grooves along the back, so there's one, two, three, four...
然后这里有两个螺母来上螺丝，然后上完就行了！
and then two spots for the offsets to uh, screw into and uh that's it!
所以呢，这个设计还算有趣。
So, that's kind of an interesting design.
Drop it!
啊，说是有趣，实为恼人。
Ugh, by interesting design, I mean terrible.
烦人至极:-(
Super annoying.
好吧，这大概应该行了。
Okay, uh, it's mostly in there.
这里本应要插另一个插槽，但是呢
This one is supposed to have another one go in right here, but uh...
这些缓存把这玩意给盖上了！也就是第四个。
the cache is actually covering the spot...  where the fourth one would go,
所以就先这样吧，但至少它固定住了，也上了一个螺丝，另一个也正好对齐。
so I'm just kinda gonna let it be what it is, but it is at least mounted in there and it's got a screw and the other ones are in place,
所以这是四个固定点，就是这个角的有点松，所以要小心。
so it's four points, it's just this corner is a little loose, so gotta be careful with that.
好了，现在我要继续给主板上电源了。
Alright, let's go ahead and plug in the power supply to the motherboard here and...
Errr，用这种插头。理论上这怎么插都行，但你肯定想让它们一个方向插。
Uh, with these, in theory, they will fit either way, but you only wanna put 'em in one way,
像将要完成的其他事情，如果你不这么做的话，你也许会搞坏什么玩意:-(
like so many of the other things in here, and if you don't, then you might blow something up,
所以这里是两条黑线相挨，
so black to black is the idea here, so of course, the black cables go side by side.
如果它们都在两边，那就很不好了。
And if they're opposing, then uh, it's not good.
你得摇摇摆摆地将其插入。
You kinda have to wiggle them in place.
再看看，应该行了。
Let's see. There we go.
好了。
Alright.
好了，下一步很有意思，当然，这不是字面意思。
Oh, here's a fun part, and by that, I mean not at all.
这是机箱前面引过来的线，
These are all the things for the front of the case, so...
包括蜂鸣器、加速键、指示灯，甚至还有前面的锁。
and the things like PC speakers, turbo switch,  LEDs, and even the little key in the front.
这些总得在主板上找个安身之处。
It's all got to plug into the motherboard somewhere.
除了这个硬盘指示灯，这个应该插在一会我要装得控制卡上。
Except for I think the hard drive LED, that's actually going to plug into the controller card once I get that installed, but uh...
啊，好吧。
Uh... good.
好吧，底下有些东西是给标出来了，但不是全部。
Ugh, okay. So it does have some of these connectors labeled down here, but not all of them.
所以呢，这可是个痛苦，这也意味着......
Uh, so... That's kind of a pain and it means...
开始Google一下......
Start looking up online...
指针定义是啥，这是个啥......
what the pinouts are for this thing, which it looks like...
https://www.elhvb.com/webhq/
这是我在一个超老的网站，叫"Motherboard Manuals Data & More"找到的定义。
Yeah, there's a jumper manual on that old classic MBarron site, "Motherboard Manuals Data & More."
所以......好吧。
So... uh... yeah.
看着网站来搞懂这是啥。
Let's follow this and see what we got.
好吧，不得不说这是......正确的:-P
Okay, I'm going to say that that... is correct.
当然，要不对的话，那开机就会有问题了。
And if it's not, then I will know once we turn this thing on.
好的，接下来咱们来啃这堆大个控制卡。
Alright, let's go ahead and get the unwieldy controller card connected.
把它们插进去后希望它们喜欢。
And put it in this slot and hope it likes it there.
要我说，我会把它搁在这，但是......想了也没用。
If I were thinking, I would put it up here, but uh... I'm not thinking.
然后把网卡搁在这。
And put the networking card in here...
挺好。
Sweet.
好的，把这大个声卡放在这。
Oh... giant sound card right here...
好的，我知道我把这个VLB插槽给占了，但是我还有两个，所以没什么可担心的。
And yes, I know I'm taking up the VLB slot right there, but we've got two more. I'm not worried.
好的，声卡在这。接下来要装的是
Alright, the sound card here. I'm actually going ahead and plug in
这个由光驱引出的传声线，来让CD音乐传入这里来播放。那么这个要插在这里。
uh, this is like the audio interface cable for the CD-ROM to allow CD audio to pass through to it, so that's going to go right there.
然后这头再插入光驱的后面。
And then this'll plug in to the back of the CD-ROM drive.
然后终于，显卡粉墨登场。
And finally... the video card.
这个要搁在这里，然后就要麻烦了因为这里的VLB口有点难处理。
It'll go right here and these are kinda tricky because the VLB part of it is a little unwieldy.
然后这个螺丝妨碍我装卡了，那咱就......
And this screw at the bottom was getting in the way of putting the video card in place, so...
就这样。
There we go.
下面的VLB口有点紧。
A tight fit in those uh, VLB portions down there, but...
终于，大概所有的控制卡都装完了吧:-)
Alright, that's pretty much all  the cards plugged in, I guess!
然后这后面是一堆老式接口之类的。
And that is a proper assortment of ports and whatnot in the back.
让我心情愉悦尽管......这个线落单了:-(
Makes me very happy even though...  this thing seems to wants to leave.
好啦，该把光驱放在这里了。
OKay, time to... drop this floppy drive in here.
现在我没注意，但是呢我实际上......
Now I didn't mention it, but I have actually...
尽我所能把这个光驱整个清理了一遍。你要想的话，
gone through and cleaned out the inside as much as I could. You can use like a...
你也可以用磁头清理盘，或者像我一样伸进去，用吸尘器吸出，保证里面
disk cleaner if you want to, or you can just go inside like I did, and just vacuum it out, made sure everything was all...
完好清洁，然后给轨道上油，
nice and clean in there, and then you lube up the rails...
用点合适的电子用机油，通常是白色的，锂基的机油，记得应该是吧。
with uh, some appropriate like electronics lube. Usually that's like a white... lithium-based lubrication, I believe, is... what it is? So...
是呀，要保证这个工作良好。
Yeah, just to make sure that it works nicely.
因为这些东西经常年久失修。当然稍微修修就能用，但是呢
'Cause those... will absolutely crap out over time. They'll usually be repairable, you know, you could get 'em working again, but...
你要没处理好的话，软驱能相当烦人，尤其是大软驱。
5¼ inch floppy drive, especially, can be really finicky when they're not properly maintained.
现在咱来插下电源线和数据线之类的东西吧。
Start putting in some uh... power and data cables and things like that.
那么这个就是从声卡引出来的传声线，而这头呢要插回......这个CD光驱。
So here's that uh, audio cable is going to the sound card. It's going to go back to the... CD-ROM.
就在这头。
Right over there...
emm，来看看。
Uh... let's see...
软驱在这个上面.......
That floppy drive is up there...
看上去这个三吋半软驱已经接上电源了，这确实挺好。
Looks like the power is still connected to the 3½ inch already, so that's useful.
而我在用这个玩意接软驱和电脑时很费劲。
So this is something that's always kind of tricky when putting floppy drives in and connecting them all up, so...
这种面条线（软驱数据线）一般没有明显标出“针一”之类，或者说，这里有个红线头给你指示。
These uh, didn't have any much of a notable like Pin 1 or usually, there's a red stripe here.
这种好像上面有一个，有个小点点之类的吧......
This one kind of has one, I guess, it's kind of like little speckles, but...
来辅助判断朝哪个方向来插入这个软驱，所以呢......
that's supposed to indicate which way this is  gonna plug into the back of the floppy drive, so...
那么，这个红色的......这个针一应该朝向这头。
Uh, it- it's supposed to, the red part... Pin 1 is supposed to be facing the direction...
这个是电源线的方向，然后是这个软驱......
of where the power plugs in and then this floppy drive...
至少对于这个三吋半的，它的右面应该是那根电源线，所以这意味着那根红色的应该对着它。
at least for the 3½ inch here, it goes in on the right, the power does, so that means the red part should be facing that.
然后就这么插进去。
And there we go.
就这样插好了:-)
Got it plugged in.
然后这个将要这样插入这个大软驱。
And then this is going to plug into the 5¼ inch drive and these can only go in one way.
然后呢就是这样。
And that's... that way.
就这样装好啦！
So that's plugged in.
好好高兴高兴:-)
Sweet!
好的，三吋半上的电源已经装上。
Um, power is already plugged in for the 3½ inch,
所以只要插这个大软驱。
so just plug this one into the 5¼ inch floppy drive there.
那么这个就是我说的装硬盘的小盒子。
So here's the caddy that I was talking about that the hard disks go into.
然后这个东西呢实际上是
Uh, it actually goes in here...
放在这里，然后在后面上螺丝，所以你得提前把这个玩意拿出来，要不然
in that, and screws into the back, so you have to like take this thing out, or else you can't get to uh...
你什么东西都放不进去，但是呢
actually putting anything  in... side of there, so...
把硬盘放进去还算容易。你仅需
Simple enough, though. You just...
将其如此滑入，大概就做这些事了吧。
slide in there like that, I believe, and that's pretty much I all I gotta do.
当然实际上，我还得设置一堆跳线来告诉电脑这是我唯一的硬盘。一般来说
Well of course, I do have it set to be the only drive in there with those little jumper pins, which usually tells you what to do
在硬盘的后面......上面......反正是铭牌之所在。
on the back, or the top of the drive where the label is.
只要将其对齐......天啊，这是什么垃圾设计？
Just gonna line these up. God, I hate this design.
好吧，我才意识到
Okay, so I just realized something.
这是一个早期的索尼大法光驱，它们得用索尼专用接口。
This is an early Sony CD-ROM drive, and that have like a Sony interface,
然后这个就是对应的电缆。我刚想插进去
and this is the cable that you can use with it, and I was just gonna plug it in.
我就突然想起：“等会儿，这电脑没有口插啊！
”I'm like, "Wait a second...  I don't have anywhere to plug that in... in the rest of the computer here."
额，这声卡上倒有点空去
Uh, there's like spaces to do...
插些不同的接口和古董啥的。
you know, different interfaces and whatnot on the AWE32 and...
控制卡也已经插满了，而且也没有一个适配接口。
I've got some things on the controller card that are all filled. Yeah, none of them are going to fit that.
我实际上也有这种有索尼接口的控制卡，你看这也标着
I do actually have a controller like the Sony, which just plugs in right here, you can see actually says
“索尼大法专用光驱口”
"SONY CDROM"
但是你看啊，这东西像是把一堆诸如声卡之类累赘的东西搞在了一起，我不需要。
But, you know, this is like a sound card and other things that I just... I don't *need*.
所以我接下来要做的是把这个索尼光驱拆下来，它很经典，但我不想再插控制卡了。
So what I'm gonna do is swap out this CD-ROM here, the Sony, it's a classic, but I don't want other cards in there.
尤其是两个声卡冲突之类的问题我能给解决，但现在我不想干。那咱就拆了它！
Especially audio ones potentially conflicting and I could probably make it work, but I just don't want to, so screw it!
好的，你这不靠谱的，给我下去！
Alright, you weirdo. Get out of there!
在这再放个更合适的。
Put something much more appropriate in here instead.
我刚翻出曾经从附近的Circuit City搞来的
I picked up something at the local Circuit City just a few minutes ago,
创新生产的全新未拆封Blaster二倍速光驱。
a brand-new in box Blaster CD-ROM 2x by Creative.
而且呢，让我伤感的是，Circuit City早就黄了，但是这个呢
And no, Circuit City has been out of business for friggin' ever, which it makes me very sad, *but* this...
这个已经吃灰很久了，而且呢，总想着最终我会在一个合适的时候拆包安装。
I have had this for a while and uh, well, figure I may as well open it up and install it in here.
因为我想它们应该能很好地与其它部件协调工作，而且这还附带着控制卡和线缆。
because uh, this'll work just fine with what I've got, and it also includes... an interface card and cable.
好吧，既然是在录节目，咱们来开箱吧。
Well, since we're here, may as well do an unboxing.
这种感觉真好。我不记得
It's pretty cool to actually... I don't remember...
我有这玩意有多久了，但我老想开箱了而且
how long I've had this, but it's been quite a while and I've been wanting to open it up anyway and...
在这雨天中使用。
just use it for a rainy day.
所以咱来看看。
So let's see.
Woo，好家伙。
Ooh, look at that!
全新的呢！
Brand-new!
太棒了。
Very cool.
所以呢，这里有一包线缆......不对，是两个。
So... you got the little baggie here with the cable and uh... another one of those.
这个传声线接口与这个有点些许不同，反还行。
This is actually gonna have a different end connector for the audio... so it's a good thing it came with that.
Oh Yeah! Feels♂Good:-)
Mmm... I like this, this is really cool.
我那时经常嫉妒......羡慕我朋友有一个
Was always jealous of these- or  envious of my friends that uh, had one...
这种Creative光驱，来看看。
uh, Creative CD-ROM, look at that.
“MPC2 - Multimedia PC（多媒体电脑）”标准
"MPC2 - Multimedia PC" standard.
肯定工作良好，全新的啊！
Adheres to that just fine. Brand new!
Woo，这可太好了。
Ooh, that's really cool.
好吧，这实际上是1995年生产的！那这一定是之后的廉价再版了。
Uh, made in 1995, actually! So this must have been a later like, re-release budget thing.
我估计这就是为什么是这种包装而且上面写着“特大优惠！”了。
I guess that makes sense with the packaging and like the whole, "Value!"
那么这个就是控制卡了。
So here is the controller card.
然后这个呢，看上去就是一个8位ISA控制卡。
And this... looks like just an 8-bit ISA.
是这样的。
Yep.
那么板子上就这些东西而且呢
So that'll just drop right in there and um... check it out.
这个东西十分简洁！钱摆在那了，但是，这个很讨我喜欢啊！
This thing is so clean! Makes sense, but I mean, it really is!
你再看，这里好像可以插那种索尼大法光驱。
You know, it looks like I could actually hook in that Sony drive on this one, but uh...
但我不装，因为这个创新光驱更让我怀旧。
No, I'm gonna go with the Creative because I have more nostalgia for that anyway.
再看看这里有啥。确实挺好。
See what else we get in here. This is pretty cool.
额，这里有一个“感谢购买”注册卡，这个光驱的说明书。
Uh, we get... "Thank You" registration card, a User's Guide for the Blaster CD-ROM 2x.
“你见过它们嘛”，这波吟唱lttstore.com
"Have You Seen These Faces?" My God.
这本说明书相当的厚啊！好么！
There's some pretty hefty documentation here, look at all this!
好家伙了！
Good grief!
这个呢，在DOS电脑中装一个光驱不是很轻松，尤其是再来一个Windows3.1。
Well, installing CD-ROM support in DOS is no easy task sometimes, especially Windows 3.1 too.
这里有个附录。
There's an Addendum.
然后再看看，这里有一个装有软件的软盘。
And uh, looks like we have a floppy disk for some software.
我到底破不破坏文物呢？
Do I wanna open this or not?
还是狠心拆了吧。
I think I do.
嗯，外面雷神震怒。
Mm, thunder outside.
果然，光驱的驱动盘！
Oh yeah. Sound Blaster CD-ROM installation disk.
二十一年没见天日了。
Not seen in 21 years.
挺好的。
Very cool.
好的，这可省了老大功搜驱动了。但是呢，我还是想要
Well, this will make it a heck of a lot easier to set up. But... I was hoping to do a like, figure out...
找到那个索尼大法驱动并且能使它工作，但这个
where I was gonna get the drivers and things for that Sony drive and how to make that work, but...
处理起来就简单了。
this is about as simple as it gets.
所以应该是接对了。
So yeah, I was right. Um...
这个插口正好可以插在这个声卡上。
The cable that the Creative CD-ROM drive comes with actually plugs directly into the AWE32 sound card,
所以我就可以不用这个控制卡了。这张卡还是挺有用的。
so I don't even need to use this guy at all.  This is a very useful card to have
能插这个索尼和创新的光驱，所以就很不错。
for that Sony and Creative drive uh, ports right there. That's really cool.
有点紧！
A tight fit!
无论如何这看上去好多了。
I like the look of this much better anyway.
不用上色之类的，但是呢
Not necessarily the coloring or anything, but that's just...
我曾经在好多朋友亲戚家里看见过这个......
I remember seeing so many Creative drives on friend's and family's computers that...
天啊，我好想要一个啊！
Oh man, I always wanted one.
是啊，所有东西都装好了，看上去真耐人！
Oh yeah, everything's in here. Looking good!
这理线水平也是......没谁了:-P
Cable management is... top notch.
但是呢，只要能用，
Uh... but you know, if this works...
我就不那么关心了。
I don't really care too much.
见证奇迹的时刻到了!
Moment of truth, see if anything works.
电源已经按下。
There's the power.
好啦，有信号了。Oh Yeah！
Ooh, got a signal. Yes!
16M内存，这个是主板信息。
16 megs of RAM, there's the motherboard.
听见硬盘运转了。
I hear the hard drive.
好的，侦测到了。“C:设备初始化失败”，好吧，这个......我早想到了:-|
Ooh, it detected. C: drive failure.  Well, that's... kind of expected.
我没觉得这是个......好的，66Mhz的CPU。
I don't think there- okay, 66 megahertz...
看上去很酷啊！
It's all looking pretty cool.
当然，它没找到操作系统。这就很......
Yeah, it's missing the operating system, that's...
好吧，这里呢......
Alright, so...
好像是......没侦测软驱B:
Uh... don't have... floppy drive B: detected there.
我也想到了，所以咱们重启然后看看BIOS吧。
Kinda makes sense, let's restart this thing and get it into the setup program.
各位客官看看，这就是我特别喜欢的BIOS。
And check this out, alright? So this is what I was *really*... I just love this BIOS.
来看看，这就像是Atari ST电脑界面之类的？反正看上去很像。（译者注：AMI在操作界面上还带开历史倒车:-\）
Look at this. It's like a... an Atari ST or something, it just... it has that sort of look to it.
这个呢看上去很超前。好的，咱来看看......这个时间日期。
It's really cool. Okay, so let's take a look here... Date and time...
我的天，这么准的吗！
Wow, it already knows?
这是啥情况？
What the heck, man!?
这很不错了。
That's pretty cool.
说真的，这个令人印象深刻。我自己都没有调。
Seriously, that's impressive. I have not set this myself.
肯定是有人提前给调好了，看看这个......
Whoever had this thing before me must have like, set it...
哇，它和现在时间基本上是同步的！
Wow, it has kept track of the time...
差个几分钟，那也相当可以了，对吧。这里的电池绝对是还有很多电。
Within like a few minutes, that's... pretty amazing, alright? That battery must still be pretty good in there.
因为我没有看这个电池是否有电，也没拿出来。
Cause yeah, I didn‘t check the uh, CR2032, I didn't take it out... or anything.
这就很令我吃惊了。
That's genuinely impressive to me.
所以我不得不说，这就有点......
So... I'm... gonna say that maybe...
好的，咱来看看这是，硬盘C: 呃，这是
Yeah, let's try that and see what happens. Hard disk C:, ooh, it's...
居然是用户模式，这模式对吗？
It's user-set, is that what I really want?
我甚至没看到这个硬盘被正确识别的消息，
I didn't even see if it was detecting it as the correct drive, um...
看上去我可以删掉这个C:,咱们来看看。
Looks like we can detect C:, let's see what that is.
是的，这样就对了。Wow，它就这样删掉了它。看见了吗，这就是好BIOS，我耐死这个了！
Yeah, that's correct. Wow, it detected it nicely. See, yeah, I *love* this BIOS, it's so cool! Look at this!
军绿色BIOS！
ARMY MODE BIOS!
柔和色的！天蓝色的！
PASTEL, SKY!
这就有点Windows 2.0 那味的了，是不是很酷啊！
This is like Windows 2.0 kinda crap here is what it looks like, isn't this great?
我太喜欢了，这个真让我愉悦:-)
I love this, this makes me so happy!
好的，稍微等我会，我得移一下相机。
Okay, let me... move the camera here for a sec,
来看看！
Check it out.
显示屏上写的是工作在66MHz频率下。
Uh, the turbo is displaying the 66 megahertz right there. Um...
我不知道这个加速键是否有用......
I don't know if this is functioning...
我也许一会再来看看，但是这个
I probably should check that here soon. But anyway, um, basically...
这个显示器显示得是正确的，“系统运行速度”是“快”，
What this is asking right here on the uh, the screen, "System Boot Up Speed" is in "High,"
所以当你按下这个“加速键”的时候，它应该会降速以适应早期软件。
so when you press the turbo button, it'll go down to like the lower uh, compatible mode for lower speed.
剩下的看上去还行。
Rest of this is lookin' pretty good.
好啦，现在不报错了:-)
Oh sweet, no error that time.
很好！完美！无瑕！
Awesome! Awesome！ Awesome!
好吧，之前为了测试，我用了一下这个硬盘。
Alright, so... yeah, I have actually used this hard drive as something else before just to test it out.
这里好像不是完整的DOS 6.22。
It doesn't actually have like full DOS 6.22 on there.
看看，这个上来就问时间之类奇怪的东西，看上去就只有COMMAND.COM（相当于Linux的Bash）。
Like see, it's asking for time and date and weird crap, it's really just like COMMAND.COM and that's it.
但是我不知为何......放了个Keen Dreams游戏。
Uh, but I did actually put uh Keen Dreams on there, um... I don't remember why.
Keen Dreams!
很好！
Neat!
看看蜂鸣器是否工作良好，我线头接对了吗。
See if the PC speaker works and I connected that correctly.
好吧，我听不见:-(
Ooh, I don't hear it!
还是没有，看上去它罢工了。
Nope, doesn't seem to be working.
所以又有活干了，但是修好的希望很大。
So we got some things to sort out, but this is very promising.
好吧，现在有一个有点意思的问题要解决，
Okay, so, this is gonna be... interesting to try to fix.
全新的光驱，当你按下“弹出“时，来看看，
Brand new CD drive, uh, when you hit the eject button, check that out.
这就想当缩头乌龟了。
That's as far as it opens.
虽然是全新的，但是嘛......我没觉得有多好。这玩意比我想的还廉价。
For brand new, uh... I am not impressed. This is more of a budget release than I thought.
来吧，拆开看看。
Alright, so check it out...
这整个后面......
This whole... back part here, uh...
它应该走得更多。
it's supposed to look... more like *that*...
然而呢，它好像只想出来那么一点:-(
and instead, it's like coming out of that little area in there...
然后这就给顶破了，真不敢相信。
and is all busted up. I can't believe it.
全新未拆封，连盒子都没有被损毁......
Brand new in the box, the box has not even been harmed...
再整个看看......这好歹是新的啊。
Yeah, I mean, you saw it looked like... well, brand new.
呃，我来看看我能修好这个吗。要修不好，我就又得用那个索尼大法了。
Um, let's see if I can fix this, but if not, I might be going back to the Sony. Good grief.
好吧，这要能用就见鬼了。
OKay, I will be surprised if this works.
但是这又能工作了。那么我就只是......
But, there we go. So I was able to just...
只是把这个部件拔出来，然后再塞回去，反正就是它本应该在的地方。
literally take this assembly, I picked it up and plopped it back where it was. Or where it's supposed to be.
我还在这之后把这块橡胶复位了！
我猜它出厂时就是这样，这可真是......忒廉价了吧！
I guess it just came from the factory like that. That is... ridiculously cheap!
我是说，这个部件整个就很廉价。天啊！买着这个可是倒霉了。
I mean, this whole assembly is just really cheap. Ugh... that's unfortunate.
好多了。
Much better.
那么我把这个光驱修好了，但这个还有一个问题需要解决。
So I've got the wonky CD-ROM drive figured out, but I do have another one to... another problem to sort now.
那么这两个软驱都能工作，但是它们都没那么方便。
So... the A: and B: drives are reading, but they're not exactly... reliable.
你看，电脑都认，但是我要读盘的话......
Like, they're recognizing just fine, but when I try to read a disk...
呃，就得到了这个该死的“读取A盘时出现一般错误”:-o
\Uh, I get this horrible "General failure reading drive A,"
不幸的是这个错误过于常见。
which is... unfortunately a pretty common problem...
我现在要读取B驱动器，为此我要插个盘。
for these. I'm going to try to access the B: drive now. Oh, let me put the disk in there.
额，再来一遍。
Uh, try that again.
然后这个看上去
And this one typically seems...
正在读盘......
to read things...
是的，它成功地读出来了！
Yeah, it read that just fine.
这个之前有几次没成功，所以呢......动手时间又来了:-(
I've had a couple times where it hasn't though, so...  you know, I'm gonna check the drives themselves.
检查线缆，检查控制卡，反正可能有好多问题呢。
Check the cable, check the uh controller card, uh, there's a bunch of things this could be.
还有可能这玩意本身就是坏的，毕竟我之前从来没用过。
It could also just be that this is a bad drive. I've never actually tried that 3½ inch drive before.
而这个我之前在别的机器上用，所以说，咱们开搞！
You know, this one usually works in the other machine that I've used it on, so... well, here we go!
看看软驱是否坏掉的方法就是试试另一个三吋半软驱然后呢......
Easiest way to check it really quick is just to try another 3½ inch drive here and uh...
好吧......
Well...
好吧，还是报那个错，所以应该是别的问题。
it's getting the same error, so it's probably something else.
好吧，经过长达四十分钟的瞎拧一通，尽我所能地
Okay, after 35-40 minutes of screwing around with everything I could,
重插电缆，重插控制卡之类的，我简直是
replacing cables, replacing disks and cards man, I frickin'-
把整个都改了一遍，这真的是......:-|
I put in a whole- I switched around everything, really.
那么我把声卡插在了下面，然后我还
So the sound card's at the bottom now, and I also put in this uh...
插了我有的另一个控制卡。
another controller card that I had.
额，实际上是一张VLB卡，你可以在此看见。
um, which is actually a VLB card, you can kinda see it there.
但实际上这个与那个普通的ISA没什么两样。
But it's basically is the same as the one I had in there that was just normal ISA,
控制一堆设备，然后插上这个老软驱然后就是见证奇迹的时刻！
hooked everything up, and uh using the same old floppy drive and look here!
终于正常工作了！
Everything's fine.
非常不错！
Perfectly fine.
所以说，好像是线缆上的问题，已经解决了。
So... somewhere along the line, it has been fixed...
我忘了在哪的问题了。
I don't give a crap where.
好的，现在A:驱动器工作良好。
Well, now that I've got a working A: drive...
现在该装 M$-DOS 6 了，准确说是6.22。
It's time to install MS-DOS 6, or specifically 6.22.
也许最终还要装Windows 3.1。
Probably install Windows 3.1 eventually as well.
但是呢......反正你得先装DOS，也就是我接下来要做的事情。
But uh... we're just gonna you know... gotta have DOS first, so that's what we're gonna do.
啊，这个经典的微软系统安装程序，好像他们用到
This classic setup for Microsoft operating systems，they used this for...
呃，应该用到Vista之类的吧，应该是吧。（译者注：实际上是XP，Vista之后的就是wim安装了）
Man, 'till what? Windows Vista or something? Maybe...
“用ScanDisk（扫描磁盘）解决磁盘问题！”磁盘有问题？只要......诊断它们！修复它们！
"Fix it with ScanDisk!" Disk problems? Just... diagnose them! Correct them!
我确信这个有时有用，但是，你知道吗?
I'm... sure it probably... works for some things, but, you know what?
有多少人真用到ScanDisk？
Who ever really used ScanDisk?
Woo，这是个好征兆。
Oh, this is going to be good.
好的，我已经把蜂鸣器给装上了，那么这个Keen Dreams应该有蜂鸣器音效了。
Aw yeah, and I... plugged in the PC speaker, so  Keen Dreams should have PC speaker sound now.
这个蜂鸣器音效是开启的。
The actual PC speaker noise... on.
蜂鸣器声音！
PC speaker noise!
听上去太棒了！
Oh, it sounds so cool.
好的，我猜现在是时候装上这个光驱驱动来看看这个光驱能不能用了。
Okay, I guess we'll try setting up the CD-ROM drive now and see if my quick repair worked.
好的，就是这样。
Oh yeah, it's uh... just, that.
再看看这里有啥......
So let's see what we got here...
这就像是......好像装上Windows 3.1后还得这样装一遍。
It's like you'll uh... I probably will only have to do the same installation when I get 3.1 on here.
但是这个是DOS版本安装程序！
But... this is the DOS installer!
那么咱继续......SBCD工作良好。
So... let's see what we got. SBCD works fine with me.
好吧，我猜它是这样，因为我并没有改掉......
Oookay, I'm assuming it's that, since I didn't change...
好吧，实话实说，我不太确定！呵呵:-|
Actually, you know, I'm not sure! Heh heh.
也许我应该查一下因为我把它插在了声卡上，而不是它的原装控制卡。
Maybe I should've checked that because I'm actually plugging this into the AWE32, not the... card that it came with.
读出来了！
Oh good!
好吧，至少这里有......好吧，它还没睡醒呢。
Well, it's at least got this, I don't know...  Ooh, it's not ready. Huh.
这个嘛，我还得改下地址来把它叫醒。
It, yeah, so I might need to switch that address...
好的，现在我们来装声卡驱动。
Okay, now it's time to install the AWE32...
这个完美的声卡。
wonderful sound card here!
从这个原装软盘读取。
Of the original floppy disks!
然后呢，咱们来看看这个“自定义安装”。
And uh, yeah, let's just... well, let me see what's in the "Custom" here.
好家伙，这堆全家桶!
Oh my. All sorts of crap.
好多我不太需要的东西，尤其是这个Windows这列的，因为呢
A lot of things I don't necessarily need, especially because there's uh, Windows stuff that I just...
我现在还没装Windows呢！
I don't even have Windows on here right now.
好吧，这就有趣了，这些设备我全都没有，但是呢......试试看，兴许有用。
So yeah, this is interesting. I don't exactly have any of these drives, but... you know, maybe this'll work...
咱们来看看......
We'll see...
你会看见刚才跳过去的这些IRQ（终端请求）和DMA（直接存储器访问）之类的东西吗？好吧。
You see all that stuff that just went by earlier about the IRQ and DMA settings and things like that? Well...
那玩意要处理起来相当痛苦！
There's a reason that can be such an absolute *pain*.
这是因为所有都要经过这的硬件：所以控制卡之类的
and that is because each piece of hardware that goes in there: all the cards and stuff,
它们都要有这个IRQ和DMA设定，基本就像这个内存地址然后
they're gonna have IRQ and DMA settings that basically is like memory addresses and
就知道在哪里去寻找这些东西了。当然这两硬件如果恰好是一个设定的话
the system knowing where to look for certain things and whatnot, and if they happen to have the same settings....
它们就会因为寻找同一个地址而冲突，或者因为其他的事情而冲突。
Uh, they can conflict or if they're looking in the wrong space, they can conflict, and all sorts of things... that can conflict.
反正这个玩意相当烦人！
It's... a wonderful, terrible thing!
现在咱们运行Duke Nukem 2来测试音效。
Let's try some Duke Nukem 2 as a test... for the sound.
我不太清楚这个AWE32音效听起来如何，是不是有点像波表之类的，但是我至少我要试试Sound Blaster音效和AdLib音效。
I know it's not exactly AWE32 like, tier wavetable stuff, but... eh, I'll at least try Sound Blaster and AdLib.
好吧，情况不妙，没有音乐。
Ehhh, it isn't promising, no music.
好吧，至少能用Sound Blaster音效，像PCM采样之类的，但是没有AdLib合成音效，或者说......
Okay, so we've got Sound Blaster sound,  like PCM audio, but no AdLib, or...?
毁灭公爵：“我回来了。”
Duke: "I'm back."
好吧，这就有意思了，我好像没有......
Well, that's fascinating. I don't think I've ever uh... heh heh...
好吧，这个已经开启了。
Yeah, it's turned on.
好吧，这个是声卡的配置和测试工具，那么我应该会听到......
Okay, so this is the testing utility/diagnostic utility for the AWE32, so we should be able to...
“八位音效测试！”
[♪ Music & VO ♪]: "8-bit testing!"
“八位音效测试”，好的，我听到了。
LGR: "8-bit testing!" Okay, so we got that.
“16位音效测试！”
[♪ Music & VO ♪]: "16-bit testing!"
好的，这个挺好。
OKay, that's good.
此为FM合成器音乐测试
[♪ FM Synthesis Music ♪]
此为高级波表音乐测试
[♪ Advanced WavEffects Music ♪]
看上去应该都能用......
Everything seems to be working...
要我说，这个挺好。
Very well, I might say.
好吧，所以这还行吧。也许这玩意刚才......还没醒盹？
Uh... so that's cool. Maybe it just needed a friggin'... be stupid.
好吧，原来就是音量太小了，那就好解决了。
It is just... insanely low volume, okay, well, we know how to fix that.
好的，咱们先退出然后呢......
Alright, let's get out of here and get back to the uh...
然后这个软件可以调节所有的音量之类的设定。
So this is where you can adjust like the volume for... all sorts of things, really.
然后呢，是的，如果我们要
And uh, yeah, if we... if we want to...
调下声道平衡之类的话，这个也行，但就有点......
Um... some equalizer settings and things like that in here too, but uh...
我这时开始把录音线给搞乱，因为录音效果不好，而且还有破音。
好吧，我运气不佳，没有把这个光驱
So, I haven't had uh, much luck getting the CD drive to work...
和这个声卡良好协作，所以我现在要用这个卡来
with the sound card, so I'm gonna actually try it with the card it came with...
看看这个光驱是否能用。
just to see if indeed the CD drive is working because...
我也不知道，我是说，也许会将一切都搞砸了。
I don't know, I mean, it could be screwed up for all I know.
另一个问题是这个主要扬声器输出口经常破音，
Another thing I've noticed is that the main speaker output here is really crackly, like...
好吧，我是说，这张卡之前保持不佳，所以我要做的是
Uh, I mean, it's seen better days, anyway, this card, so what I'm gonna do is...
用一点这个DeoxIT接口清理剂，这个对清理
Uh, use a little bit of this DeoxIT contact cleaner, which is good for,
额，清理接口之类的东西有用吧。
well, cleaning contacts and stuff
尤其像是这个氧化的音频口。
and especially like deoxidizing audio ports.
那么，理论上，这个应该能延缓氧化之类的吧。
So... in theory, this is supposed to just... break up the oxidization and some other crap that's in there.
对我许多的音乐设备都有效，所以呢......
Works really well for a lot of audio equipment that I have, so...
希望这个也能解决这个毛病吧，所以让我们坐和放宽一会儿，
Hopefully, it will resolve my problems here too, so we'll let that sit for a while, kind of...
稍微翻译一下然后再喷点，
let it go and then spray it a little bit more,
然后让其干掉然后，把它们都清理出来。然后最终，希望出来的音质能好些吧。
then let it dry off and uh, get all that crap out of there. And hopefully, we'll have some good audio.
上天保佑啊！
Please...
呀！快来看看！
Oooh! Ooh! Ooooooh!
好极了！
Okay!
好的，所以这应该能工作了吧。把那个创新的
Sweet, alright. So I guess that- that worked. Uh, putting in the Creative card...
不是声卡，而是这个光驱控制卡。好极了！
not the sound card, the interface card for the CD-ROM. Awesome!
那么我们也就可以访问D:驱动器了。
So we should have D: accessible...
好的，光驱转起来了！希望这能用吧......
Oh, I hear it spinning, hopefully it's okay...
听上去像是有东西在刮蹭。
It sounds a little bit like it's rubbing up against something, which it probably is.
你听，七老爷又在......
*Grinding Noise*
好吧，听上去不对劲。
Yep, okay, so I was afraid of that.
呃，好吧，实际上......我早就想到了。
Ngh, kind of uh... as expected, to be honest...
还好，CD没事，光驱没有划道子。但是光驱里面我稍微拧松了些，因为这玩意......
So... CD is fine, it didn't mess up anything, but the internals are a little screwed up because of the whole uh,
直说了吧，这玩意就是块废铁！
well, the fact that it's just a piece of crap.
短暂的两天之后......
好吧，这问题已经两天没解决了。但是呢，目前我是如此解决的：
Well, it's been interesting couple of days, but uh, here's the solution I've got at the moment:
我随便找了个宏碁的光驱。这个确实有点新，这是个五十倍速的
I'm just using this random Acer CD-ROM drive, which is much later. It's a 50x...
我确实因为这个有点不快，因为这个没有和其他配件......
I don't like it being in here, since it doesn't fit in my whole uh...
你懂得，和九十年代早期风格相搭配。这个有点九十年代后期的，但是呢
you know, early '90s aesthetic, that's more like,  much later '90s, but uh, you know, whatever...
我不关心，因为
I don't care, because...
它至少工作而且这是个IDE驱动器。
It frickin' works and it's an IDE drive,
而且也无需把我搞好的控制卡之类的给搞好。
and I don't have to mess with any stupid controller cards or anything like that.
呃，这个确实是我犯懒了。但在可以
Eh, this is the lazy way out, but uh that's what I'm doing right now until I get a better,
换一个合适年代的光驱之前，先这样吧。
more appropriate for the era CD-ROM that actually works.
因为那个索尼大法我试了......
'Cause I tried the Sony one...
就没法用。
Eh, didn't work.
然后这个创新的，这两天来解决的问题太多，我受够了。那咱就这么用吧！
And like, uh, the Creative one, there's just so many problems I've had over the past couple of days and I'm just pissed, so here we go!
好的，现在呢，我要看看前天想试的Duke Nukem 3D能不能用。
Uh heh, here... is... see, Duke Nukem 3D that I was trying to do the other day.
就是试试装上，然后，咱们来看看。
Just trying to install this, and uh...  you know, there we go.
很好。
Excellent.
跟我所想的一样。
Exactly what I wanted to do.
现在我设置这个IDE设备就很简单了，因为正如我所说，你不必插个另外的控制卡
Now setting up these IDE drives is super simple, cause like I said, you don't need like a... an extra controller card...
或者其他的接口，这个就是IDE口，和这个硬盘用的口一样。
or any weird interfaces. It's just IDE, the same as the hard disk that I'm using.
那么，只要你用的DOS版本兼容的话，
And so, what you do for that is as long as your DOS version is compatible,
你仅需在CONFIG.SYS（功能相当于Linux的systemd）里写上就行了。:-(这里我给命名为FARTS了)-:
you can just put this into your CONFIG.SYS file (I've named this one "FARTS").
这个调用了CD1.SYS，好像就是通用的CD-ROM驱动。
It's using the CD1.SYS, which is just like a standard Oak CD-ROM file that's uh,
这个附带于许多版本的DOS。我也不知为何，我就给写进去了。
it comes with a lot of versions of DOS and I don't know, I just have it floating around.
你若需要，你可以找到的。
You can find it if you need to.
然后将其写入AUTOEXEC.BAT（DOS开机自启动软件），
And then you add this to your AUTOEXEC.BAT,
然后就能开机支持光驱了。
and this will start up the uh, actual CD-ROM capability when your computer starts.
这行告诉电脑要将光驱命名为FARTS，然后挂载于D：
This tells it to look for FARTS, which is in here, and this tells it to make it the D: drive.
然后呢
And um...
很明显你可以按你所需更改它，但是呢，我目前就先写成这样了。
Obviously you can change around some of this if you want to, but... this is how I'm doing it for now.
好的，我们赶紧拿Duke Nukem 3D测试，然后呢，
Okay, just to test out some things in Duke 3D really quick, and uh,
好吧，我已经把声卡给设置好了，音乐的处理设备也设定好了。
well, I have successfully set the AWE32 goodness in here and the music set to that as well.
看上去都是默认设置，那么......
Everything's pretty much default, so...
很好！
Nice!
听上去不佳，但是呢，先这样吧。
Kinda sounds like crap, but uh... You know, whatever.
所以咱们开搞640x480 VESA模式，因为
So let's try this 640x480 VESA mode here, um...
译者注：Duke Nukem 3D推荐使用奔腾处理器，而这个配置刚刚够运行。
呃，你懂的，这个运行肯定没有那么好。
Uh, you know what? It's- It's not going to do that at all.
额，那咱就试试，因为这个运行肯定没那么好。
Um... Let's do it anyway, because it's probably going to suck.
好吧，开始界面可以运行，但是一会你就会看见运行在
Well, we're going to get an intro screen but uh, you're going to see what happens when eh, you try to run this...
一台486上，以640x480分辨率时的样子。加载就够它喝一壶的了。
at 640x480, on a 486-66, it just...  it takes forever to load, for one thing...
但当加载成功之时......我的妈啊！
But once it does... oh my word.
好像是一帧能玩。
We might get a frame a second.
咦，好像是两帧！
Ahhh! It's like two!
两帧流畅！
Two frames!
我了个老天爷啊！
Ohhhh, man!
你知道吗，这说明这个可以工作在VESA兼容模式，在我小的时候这可令人高兴的事情。
You know, it's just the fact that it *can* do this VESA compatible mode, and that's what would have made me happy back in the day.
我无论如何都要试试这么玩游戏。
I would have learned to play this game *like this* anyway!
额，显然，这个应该在软件中更改一下设置来更好运行，
Uh, obviously, it's supposed to, it's gonna run better and adjust in software mode because um,
因为要那么运行的话太难为电脑了。
yeah- the graphics and the CPU and just *EVERYTHING* are not up to snuff to uh, to work it out that way.
啊，这样就更好了。
Oh yeah, that's a lot better already.
很好！看见开头动唤了。
Sweet! Actually got a logo that moves.
这声音拿AWE32处理确实很差。
That sound really does sound awful in AWE32 mode.
我得搞下MIDI音色库之类的东西，因为
I need to... mess with the soundfonts or something, man! 'Cause that...
你可以这样来提升效果。
You can make that sound different.
好吧，对于这个66MHz的CPU，它跑出来了它应有的水平。
Okay, so yeah, this is about what I expected for a 66 megahertz...
好吧，就算是运行在这个320x200的分辨率下，这加载......好像还是够费劲的。
So even in 320x200 here, it's just still going to... I mean, this is going to take forever to load right here.
好吧，比我想的要快。
Oh, it didn't take as long as I thought it would.
这个运行是真够慢的。那么，当你有这种龟速电脑时，
That's *really* slow. So typically, what you did, when you had a computer of this slowness,
你就要关闭细节优化，把这类东西都关掉。
was turn off the detail, turn that kind of stuff off,
甚至于把游戏画面一~~~直缩小至此，我记得我小时有时就这么打的。
and then even screen size *waaaay* down here, and I do remember playing some games like this
在我那台486。
on my 486 back in the day.
看看，这基本就可以玩了B-)
Look at that! It's almost playable.
好吧，这大小也就和两张邮票差不多。但这好歹能用，而且你也可以玩。
I mean... sure, it's just about twice the size of a postage stamp, but uh... it does work and you can play it.
这可是童年回忆啊，兄弟们！
This brings back memories, man! Oh, it really does.
我曾经有一台Packard Bell的486机器，好像也是这个66DX2处理器。
I had a Packard Bell 486, I believe it was a 66DX2 like this one.
好吧，这也就是你所能干的了。
Uh, and it... you know, this is about what it could do.
当然，那台电脑没有声卡，光驱，所以和这台电脑比就相形见绌了。但是！
Of course, it never had a sound card, never had a CD-ROM drive, so it was immeasurably less cool than this computer, BUT...
我还是对它有感情的。当时我很惊奇。等会儿，先自杀一下。这就很
I still loved it. I'm amazed. Well, kill myself, this is-
毁灭公爵：MMP
LGR (Duke VO): "THIS IS FREAKIN' AWFUL!"
但是呢，你们知道我是有多想在VESA模式兼容的电脑上玩这个游戏吗？
But yeah, you know what I wanted to play with a VESA-compatible computer?
我就是想要这样的卡，还有声卡，光驱，就为了玩这个。
I just wanted one of these cards in here, and a sound card, and a CD-ROM, just to play THIS.
这个模拟城市2000特别版......在这张光盘上。
The SimCity 2000 Special Edition... on a CD-ROM, and...
回忆又来了，我一个朋友有一个Compaq的电脑而且他家一整套都有！
it just blew me away, a friend of mine had a Compaq and it had all the things, you know?
额，我记得电脑好像也是486，但是可有个光驱啊。
NUh, I think it was also like a 66 megahertz, uh 486, but had a CD-ROM drive...
好像是创新的，然后用光驱安装，还有
I believe by Creative, even, and installed that thing, and...
声霸卡。而且呢，
Sound Blaster, and you know,
基本上，我是在攥一台1993-1994那时的主流机。
BASICALLY, I'M EMULATING that experience from around 1993-'94,
这个是我一直想要的啊！然后我不知......等我看一眼......
and this is all I wanted man, and I don't know if uh... let me see here...
SVGA显卡，512显存。
SVGA card with 512K video RAM.
好吧，这上面并没有明确告诉你这个可以
Now it doesn't actually tell you that it's gotta, like...
运行在VESA标准之类的事情，但是当你启动这个安装程序的话......
conform to this VESA standard thing, but when you run the Setup on this...
来吧，我现在来给你看看。
You know what?  I'm just gonna show you right now.
天啊！这就是安装界面。这个安装界面我魂牵梦萦了好多年了。
Aw man, okay yeah, so this right here. THIS installation screen was the *bane* of my existence for years!
所以，当我买着这个的时候，
So, when I got this...
不光冲着这个特别版，实际上，我一直都很想有一个。
Not specifically the Special Edition, but you know, this is what I wanna do.
它就是运行不了！
Uh, it didn't... it just didn't work!
因为我那是VGA显卡，而这个游戏应该是需要SVGA显卡。
Because I had a VGA card, and- and you know what? I think it had some sort of weird SVGA capability...
记得是Trident卡，我能想起来是因为我当时在想：“我的显卡太差了。”
It was a Trident card, I remember that because I remember thinking, "Oh, my video card is chewing gum."
这个是那台Packard Bells内置的，然后呢......
This was all on that Packard Bell, and uh...
你懂吗，这就有点......
You know what? It just...
emmm
Ugh...
反正这个就是装不上去。
It would not get past this, no matter what.
好的，我没填错。
Yeah, it's correct.
那么接下来呢，来看看“自定义安装”。
So, where is this in here? Let's do the Custom Install.
好的，我想起来了。我应该“完全安装”。
Now I remember going through here. We're going to do the Full.
然后呢......应该是这样吧。
And uh... I'll get to this.
然后呢，这应该把整个流程都走一遍。然后应该还有
And so, it's gonna run through all the whole installation and then what it would do is
应该还有一个安装VESA显卡驱动还是啥的过程。
there's another installation for installing the VESA video drivers and whatnot
有些电脑得装，但我没想到我的电脑就得装。
for your specific computer and I had no idea what that crap was on mine.
然后我终了没装。我在那年的圣诞夜得到的这个。
And I didn't. I got a SimCity 2000 for Christmas.
1994年，好像是。然后我就没法玩，好像花了
1994, I believe, and I couldn't run it for like...
六个月来着来处理这个VESA兼容显卡问题，
Six months or so, while I tried to figure out this VESA compatibility problem...
然后这就是这样。我记得UniVBE（一个VESA驱动）
and it was such a thing. I remember UniVBE...
还是啥的，一个小程序......看，说曹操，曹操来。
or something along those lines, an executable... Yeah, I think it just installed it.
你刚刚看见UniVBE和VESA数据啥的吧，所以这个电脑可以跑这个，而我那台老机器就不行。
you'll see some of this VESA data stuff, so this could run it, and my computer back then couldn't.
那么我现在就是在复古那时的电脑！
So I'm *building this thing to get back* at the past!
那时必须选“蜂鸣器”，但现在我才不要！
Always had to select PC speaker, but NOPE!
我们可以一路往下因为我现在可以有了！因为我搞出了这台完美的机器！
We're going to go *all-out* because I *can* now! Because I *made* something that's *amazing*!
啊！1993年差劲透了！
Ugh! Suck it, 1993!
继续！
Continue!
好的，这个也一样。
Alright, same thing for this.
1993真差劲！
Suck it 1993!
好的，安装顺利结束。
Okay, so it completed just fine.
但是在那时，它会报各种各样的错误因为
However, it would give me all sorts of errors back in the day because
该死的VESA之类的麻烦。现在我来看看这个可以启动吗。
of this VESA crap, and let me see if I can open that.
好的，那么VDTech......它就这样工作。它就把这些东西都打了出来。
Okay, so VDTech - They all did this, right, and it would bring these things up.
我当时一个都没有，最接近的就是这个Trident之类的，但这可不是Impact型号的。
I had none of these, closest I could figure is I had a Trident something, but it wasn't an Impact.
然后当时我把这些都试了个遍。
And I tried *every single* one of these.
好的，来看看。它会尝试加载，然后我就会想“天啊，这是啥情况？”
""Yeah, look at this. It would try to bring this up and it was just like, "Holy crap, what's going on?" But...
好的，来看看！
Here you go! Look at this!
VESA兼容显卡。
VESA-compliant card.
这简直......
This...
我的天啊！我太激动了因为说真的，
Oh man! I almost wanna cry because this is seriously...
我一直都梦想看到这个。这是我最最喜欢的游戏。
is what I dreamed of so much. This is my favorite game in the world.
我当时在我的朋友家玩，它们家电脑有VESA显卡。
I would play it at my friend's house, they had the VESA card,
所有折腾都是值得的！
This is worth all the hassle!
看看这个！
Right here!
哦，这真是太好了！
Oh, this is great.
来看看！快来看看啊！
Look at this! Oh, look at it!
哦，这真是太美妙了！
Oh, it's so cool!
模拟城市2000特别版。
SimCity 2000 Special Edition...
所以你们知道吗......
So yeah man...
这就是我想有这台电脑的终极目的，我没开玩笑。
This is all I wanted to do with this machine.  I'm not even kidding.
好吧，它找不到鼠标驱动，因为我还没装。
Of course it can't find the mouse driver, it's cause I haven't loaded the mouse.
不要这样嘛！！！！！！！
NOOOOO!!!
但是呢，我只要赶紧找个鼠标装上就行了。
Uh, but yeah I just need to plug in a mouse really quick.
好的，再搜了遍仓库然后我找到了这个小玩意。
Mm, digging around my storage again and found this little guy.
想想这确实是个合适的鼠标。
Figured uh... this be a good choice for a mouse.
罗技牌“你的第一个鼠标”，为IBM兼容机设计。
"Logitech First Mouse" for IBM compatibles.
“一次中键相当于两次左键！”好吧，中键就是干这个事的:-|
"Double click with one click!" Yeah, that's what the middle mouse button did.
嘿，双击键呢！
Heh, double click button!
不是什么鼠标中键，但是呢......不管了。
Not the uh, middle mouse button, but yeah, whatever.
这个能很好工作，这是个串口，而且里面都还很新呢。
It'll work for what I need, it's a serial and it's all pretty new and stuff inside.
那么，咱就用这个吧。
so... yeah, let's get this out of the way.
MouseWare Lite program 2，想装就装吧，但是你也没必要非得装。
MouseWare Lite program 2. Install it, if you want, which... you don't necessarily need to,
DOS早已内置鼠标之类的驱动。
DOS has its own sort of drivers for it and whatnot,
那咱就继续吧！
and uh, here we go.
这上面还有从GoodWill买来时的价格标签。
It still has the sticker on it from when I was at Goodwill and I got it.
但毕竟这就是一个十分基础的鼠标，十分廉价。
But yeah, it's just a *really* basic little mouse, kinda cheap.
然后这很明显还有串口转PS/2转接器，很明显，我不需要PS/2接口，因为电脑没有，而且呢
And uh, it's got this serial to PS/2 adapter on there, obviously, I don't need the PS/2 port, as I don't have one on that computer, but...
专家推荐串口。
Serial is exactly what the doctor ordered.
好的，我把这“第一个鼠标”第一次接进电脑。
Alright, I've got the First Mouse plugged into for the first time.
啊，这多好。
Ahh, so clever.
我现在要玩一下模拟城市，因为我很想玩。
And we're going to play some SimCity 2000 because... I really want to.
“正在生成地形”
"Reticulating splines..."
译者注：此为意译，实际无义。Simcity开发者Will Wright认为这个短语很酷，就用上了。后来成为笑话。
是的，正在生成地形，宝贝:-)
That's right, reticulate those splines, baby
我们把这个镇叫做
We're gonna call this...
“木纹镇”
"Woodgraintown."
然后我们在2000年开始。
And we're gonna start in 2000.
“木纹镇建立了！”
"Woodgraintown founded!"
“晴空万里，阳光普照，在愉悦的气氛中，市长Clint铲下了建立城镇的第一铲土。”
"On this joyous Sunday celebration, Mayor Clint turned the first ceremonious shovel of earth..."
然后就这么愉悦地发展了。
and things happened.
好极了！
Aw yeesss!
这个地方不错。
The good stuff right here.
那么，我们来建一个发电站......
So, let's build a power plant...
用点煤
Go with coal...
因为现在你也得用。
'cause that's the thing you do nowadays.
哇，我发觉我好久没说话了。我只是......太入迷了。
Wow, I just noticed, I'm not talking at all. I am already just... into the game.
这感觉很......
This is just...
我耐死这个游戏了。
I love this stuff.
警察局放这里。
Police right there...
好吧，咱就这么干。
Uh... let's just do... this.
为什么不呢。
'Cause why not?
在这里放点水泵。
Eh, put a water pump over here...
按计划进行。
Do those things to plan ahead.
情况进展顺利。
A fluent situation going on.
好的。
Alright.
开启猎豹模式（急速模式）。
Go with that uh, Cheetah speed.
DOS版本的急速模式不叫“African Swallow（非洲燕子）”，你只能在Windows的特殊版本中看见。
The DOS version doesn't actually have African Swallow, you only got that with the Windows version of the Special Edition here, so.
好吧，这是一个值得注意的现实。
Faux Accent VO: "Well, that is a notable fact, that is."
看看！
Look at this!
我的小镇正在繁荣起来！
My town is THRIVING!
该把它给毁了:-(
Time to blow it up.
世界末日！
"Mayday!"
街头暴动！
Riots in the streets!
市长要把整个镇子给毁掉了！我们才刚建立！
Mayor's blowing up the whole town. We just got started!
什么情况!?
What is this crap!?
哦不！
Oh no!
我很喜欢它们让其放火的方式，能够被大风大雨吹灭。
I like how they're setting on fire as they're about to be overtaken by hurricane floods.
嘿，你们知道吗！
Oh, guess not!
你们一个个都是菜鸡！
You guys just suck then!
无论如何，我就这么放着。它就是这么工作的。
Whatever, I put them there. That's just how it goes.
啊，这个游戏真是不错！
Ah, this game is awesome!
好吧，在这台486上它跑的确实......够慢。但与此同时呢
So, yeah, with the 486 it does run a tad...  slow, I mean, but at the same time...
它是用来跑都市地图的。
it was designed to run on cities
我的天！这跑的确实是够慢的。
Good grief! Systems even slower than this.
但是你看这个
But yeah, you can see like on a...
在运行这个许多人口的都市时，它还是运行得很好。我想说这个不仅仅能玩了。我当时就是这么玩的。
Even on a really populated city here, still running pretty well. I mean, it's more than playable. This is how I remember playing it, so...
这是个好游戏。
It's good stuff.
我太喜欢了！
I like this.
我耐死这个了！
I like this so much.
但我接下来要干啥呢？额，我来看看其他游戏吧。
But you know what, even though I do? Uh, let's actually go and check out some other...
其他游戏呢......我把这个打开了......来看看其他的游戏运行在这Woodgrain 486上。
some other games while uh... I have this open and um, just... show a few things in action here on the Woodgrain 486.
Norton Commander（一个文件管理器）
Norton Commander...
是啊，那时DOS命令漫天跑，干啥事都得输入命令（译者注：欢迎加入Arch Linux邪教）:-(
Yeah... there's a time and a place for a bunch of DOS commands and entering things through text, but uh...
所以说，搞到就好好用吧。
Well, if you got it, may as well use it.
:-(
译者注：每次玩这关时，我就会想到Metallica的Master of Puppets......
好的，我相信你明白了，这玩意能用。
Well, I think you get the gist of it, uh, it works.
好的，现在我对电脑的运行感到十分满意，那么现在呢
Alright, so I'm pretty satisfied with the way this thing is working at the moment, so...
最后一件事就是贴上木纹！
Last thing to do is apply the woodgrain...
好吧，我从未在一台电脑上搞过这个......
and uh, well, I've never actually done this to a computer, so...
我觉得这个应该把这个给包上，
I'm assuming I'm really just gonna... make it go all the way around and um...
尽我所能地贴得合适吧。
just stick it to it best I can.
好的，就这么做。速度慢点，挤掉泡泡。
Oh yeah, this is gonna work. Slow going trying to get all these bubbles out.
好吧，周围有多余的
Oh yesss! So I've got plenty of extra around the edges and whatnot...
得绞下去，，这些东西，但来看看!
to uh, cut off, trim...  all that kind of stuff, but look at this!
这个
That...
真是太愉悦了！
is so cool!
好的
Oh yeah...
想想我已经有这个......木纹机箱的高兴吧:-)
Think I've got myself a uh, woodgrain PC case here!
这个简直是......
That is...!
天啊，我太喜欢了！
D'aw, okay. I love this.
好的，大家来看看！
Alright. Look at *that*!
我的天啊，这个太酷了！
Ohhh, that is the coolest!
我太喜欢了！
I love it!
来吧，换个角度好好看看。
Oh man, okay. A better look at this thing here...
这对我而言太酷了！
That's so freakin' cool to me!
满眼都是木纹。
Woodgrain, woodgrain, woodgrain...
这种胡桃木质地的花纹简直是......
It's a very nice walnut kind of texture...
好极了！
Oh yes!
这真是极有品味的。
That is pure class.
现在我想说点......想想就很兴奋，
Now, I do kind of what... it kind of makes me want to...
我想把前面板再给改改，显得更加合适，就像
mess with the front of this a little bit more and make it more uh... appropriate, like...
我想，也许前面板改成黑色，比这个乳白色不知高到哪里去了。
I was thinking, maybe sort of a black instead of this beige,
然后这里再给上个银色。
and then maybe have these like a silver or something,
然后，差点把这个忘了，这个再说一遍，应该能工作。
but then, of course, that leaves this, but then again, that might work.
然后正如你所看见的，我确实找到了另一个合适的光驱。这个大概1995年生产的？
And as you might have noticed, I actually did find another CD-ROM drive that is appropriate. This was made, I think, early 1995?
然后呢，这就是那种四速的，工作良好。和那个宏碁的一样是IDE接口，
And uh, it's just a 4x... works very well, IDE drive, just like that Acer one was, and uh...
哦，这个就很......
oh, this is just...
想象创造的感觉真是太好了！
this is just so fulfilling to create.
好的，本期木纹486电脑装机视频就到这里了。（译者注：终于搞完了8-|）
Well, that's it for the Woodgrain 486 build for today, and
我希望大家看得高兴，正如我高兴装机一样。这台电脑简直是
I hope you enjoyed watching this as much as I enjoyed creating it. This is just... uh, it was so...
攥这台机器真是令人愉悦。当然，肯定有人会问
It's so satisfying to create this thing, and yeah, there might be some of you asking very legitimately like,
“你为何不去搞一台提前装好的DOS电脑呢？”
"Why not just get a pre-built DOS machine from the time?"
当然，你可以那么做。实际上，这是个好主意。
And yeah, you can do that. Great option and, in fact, there's a whole lot of things that you can do
搞台稍晚于此的Windows机器性能会比这个更强，
as far as like later Windows machines that make a lot more sense than something like this practically
尤其是你只是想玩老DOS游戏的话。
if you just wanna play some games really easily, but uh...
甚至是DOSBox，现在比较流行的方案。
Or even DOSBox, you know, fine option nowadays.
但是这个！
But this!
这可是满满的满足感啊！这是我小时的梦想成真。这就是
This is pure fulfillment. This is pure childhood fantasy come to life. This is just...
老科技的巅峰，我喜欢这个项目。把它们都攥在一块的简直是
geeky greatness, I love these kinds of projects and putting this thing together, it was just...
简直是太好了！
Oh, this is so cool.
我耐死它了！这是我最喜欢的电脑了。
I love this, man. This is like, my new favorite computer.
我......我的喜悦之情难以用语言表达了。
Ohh, I don't know, I don't have much more to say,
除了接下来的升级计划。它还不那么完美。
except that I do wanna do some more work on it. Like, it's not perfect yet.
它还需要，一些小小的就工作，
It does need uh, some little kinks worked out like,
比如，“加速键”按下后CPU频率变化不再这里显现，我也搞不明白。
for instance, the turbo button doesn't actually adjust the display here, I'm not sure why.
这个电源指示灯没法用，也许应该改一下。
I couldn't get the power LED to work, it may need to be replaced.
还有，这个声卡也是有点问题，我不知道这是不是坏的。
And uh, there's some weird issues still with the AWE32 sound card, and I don't know if the card is bad, like...
因为现在右声道
'Cause now the right audio channel on the...
没有声音，我还得把这个搞明白。
uh, audio out is just not working, I also need to address that, so...
然后我还安装了Windows 3.1
And I also want to install uh 3.1 and...
应该是Windows3.11，就用着玩，因为我很喜欢这个版本的Windows。
maybe 3.11 on here uh for Windows, just to play with that, 'cause I like that version of Windows, but...
但是呢，还有好多的......
You know... either way, this is just...
装机是多么有意思啊！
This has been so much fun to put together and uh...
感谢大家这几年的支持，让这一切都能实现。
Thank you to everyone who has supported me over the years and make these kinds of things happen.
感谢大家这几年来的关注，我也只是磕磕绊绊地为大家提供这些优秀的视频。
And thank you for watching my uh, just stumbling around trying to get something like this to happen.
真难以置信，LGR开张七年了。然后呢
This is awesome. Seven years of LGR, and this is uh...
这就是成果了(*^▽^*)
THIS IS THE RESULT!
希望能值回票价！
I HOPE IT WAS WORTH IT!
您可关注以下UP主来关注LGR：pingatsky，Douglas Jing，voodooman，某科学的小姚同志，wu_dl，雪野しらたまこ
本视频由SuperBart翻译，原作者LGR制作于2017-01
当然如果你喜欢这个视频，也许你也会喜欢我做的其他视频。
And if you enjoyed this video, then perhaps, you'd like to see some of my others.
当然，如果你关注我的话，你已经看过我的其他大作了。
Although, if you've made it this far, chance are, you have seen some of my others and, but uh, yeah.
希望大家喜欢。如果可以的话，你也可以点击这上面的视频来欣赏。
I hoped you enjoyed this and if you did, you can click some of these videos right here,
或者每周一或周五去油管来关注这些。
or stop by every Monday and Friday for more of *this* kind of stuff.
一如既往，感谢大家七年及接下来的支持。
And as always, thank you very much for watching for seven years and counting.